Guide to the Josiah K. Lilly Correspondence, 1931-1944 CAM.JKLCorr.2016
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Josiah K. Lilly Correspondence
1931-1944
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Lilly, Josiah Kirby, 1861-1948
CAM.JKLCorr.2016
46.25 Linear Feet (37 boxes)
The Josiah K. Lilly Correspondence contains correspondence regarding the impetus of the Foster Hall Collection, development, research and documentation of the collection at Foster Hall at Lilly's home in Indianapolis, Lilly's relationship with the University of Pittsburgh, and the donation and transfer of the Collection to the University to be housed in the Stephen Foster Memorial. Among the various topics covered in the correspondence are John Tasker Howard's research and publication of his biography of Foster, Evelyn Foster Morneweck's biography of her uncle, Lilly's dealings with rare book dealers, the creation of the Foster Hall Recordings and Foster Hall Reproductions, and Lilly's contact with various Foster descendants.
Scope and Content Notes
The Lilly Correspondence contains correspondence regarding the impetus of the Foster Hall Collection, development, research and documentation of the collection at Foster Hall at Lilly's home in Indianapolis, Lilly's relationship with the University of Pittsburgh, and the donation and transfer of the Collection to the University to be housed in the Stephen Foster Memorial. Among the various topics covered in the correspondence are John Tasker Howard's research and publication of his biography of Foster, Evelyn Foster Morneweck's biography of her uncle, Lilly's dealings with rare book dealers, the creation of the Foster Hall Recordings and Foster Hall Reproductions, and Lilly's contact with various Foster descendants, and the collection's transfer to the University of Pittsburgh.
Biography
The Foster Hall Collection was founded, not by a Pittsburgher or a musician, but by an Indianapolis manufacturer, Josiah Kirby Lilly, Sr. Through his generosity, the collection was presented to the University of Pittsburgh, to be housed permanently in the Foster Memorial, for view and study by the American people. Much of the remarkable revival of interest in Foster was due to the activities of Mr. Lilly. Through his collecting he brought to light hitherto unknown information and acquired materials that might otherwise have been lost. Through his publications he made important contributions to Foster bibliography. Through his gifts to libraries, schools, musical organizations, radio stations, and individuals, Foster music and literature have been widely distributed and new interest in the composer was aroused.
The love of this Indiana citizen for the music of Stephen Foster may be traced back to his youth, in Greencastle, Indiana, when he used to hear the students at Asbury College (now DePauw University) singing Foster's songs. Throughout his life, Mr. Lilly has enjoyed keenly hearing Foster's music sung or played. But it was not until 1930, when he was about to retire from business, that he became actively interested in the collecting of material relating to Foster. Some time that year, he happened to hear played a set of excellent phonographic recordings of Foster's music. It occurred to him that it might be an interesting hobby to collect the early editions of these songs he loved so well. Acting upon the advice of one of his sons, a bibliophile, Mr. Lilly wrote to several dealers in Americana, from whom he acquired a few first and early editions of Foster's songs. And then, on January 5, 1931, occurred an event which caused him to become a serious collector of Fosteriana, and to build up the most important collection in existence. On that day he acquired from a Boston dealer several hundred early editions of Foster music, including nearly one hundred first editions. He realized that he now had the most important collection of the music of America's great melodist that had yet been brought together. Yet it was obvious that it was far from complete. He had less than half the possible first editions. There must be many hundreds- possibly thousands- of early editions. His collection so far possessed no Foster manuscripts, no letters, none of Stephen's personal possessions, no pictures, no bibliography on the subject. The very incompleteness of his work so far was a challenge! He would build up his collection, fill in the vacancies, learn all he could about the man and his music, work carefully and accurately, and make his hobby a distinct contribution to American music and American history. He possessed, in the suburbs of Indianapolis, a small granite building used as a library and music hall. He placed his collection in this building, which was then named Foster Hall. The collection itself soon became known as the Foster Hall Collection.
Mr. Lilly organized the work of solving his collecting problems in businesslike fashion. Not long after the collection was founded, he realized that his interest would soon pass the stage of a one-man hobby, and that assistance would be necessary. New acquisitions were accumulating, source material was awaiting study, certain problems requiring a technical knowledge of music had arisen. The specialized aid he needed was found in the person of Walter R. Whittlesey, an able research worker and musicologist of Washington, D. C., for thirty-five years a member of the staff of the music division of the Library of Congress. As the collection grew in size, other members were added to the Faster Hall staff, in both Indianapolis and Washington. The wdrk was divided into the classifications of acquiring, research, cataloguing, mounting, and correspondence. At one time, eleven persons were engaged in carrying on the work.
Many others, not directly associated with Foster Hall, assisted in the building up of the collection. Dealers in books and music who had Foster material for sale or exchange, fellow-collectors, and all persons interested in Stephen Foster were invited to communicate with Foster Hall. For their benefit an informal magazine, entitled the Foster Hall Bulletin, was published and distributed gratuitously. This bulletin contained news of interest to the Foster collector: the discovery of new songs, reprints of Foster letters, the establishment of memorials to the composer. Each issue contained a list of the songs still needed by the Foster Hall Collection, and the prices offered for them. The relatives of Stephen Foster aided in the work. Mrs. Jessie W. Rose of Pittsburgh, granddaughter of the composer, and Mrs. Evelyn Foster Morneweck of Detroit, daughter of his brother, Morrison Foster, rendered especially valuable service. Original letters and manuscripts, personal possessions of Foster, and other source material not obtainable elsewhere were added to the collection through their cooperation. Moreover, musicians, librarians, curators, students of Americana, sent information and material. Letters were received from all parts of the United States, from Canada and Great Britain, and material poured in from every quarter and in every form.
The result, after several years of work, was a comprehensive collection of more than ten thousand separate items, carefully catalogued and prepared for preservation and use, including: original manuscripts; facsimiles of manuscripts in other collections; first, early, and modern editions of Foster's music; Foster's own possessions; books relating to the composer in whole or in part; songbooks containing his music; magazine and newspaper articles; pictures and portraits; phonograph records; broadsides; and miscellaneous Fosteriana.
One of the most fascinating of the Foster Hall studies has been the identification of original works of the composer, as distinguished from adaptations of his melodies. The number of original published songs and compositions discovered so far is 201. In addition to this number, there were over a hundred arrangements and translations which are not classified as original works. The determination of these figures was a more complicated process than the mere counting of titles. It was early discovered that many of the songs credited to Foster were not actually original compositions. Mr. Lilly has coined the word "Derivata" for adaptations of Foster melodies- a term which has become a standard part of the vocabulary of Foster collectors. The immense number of these adaptations was a source of confusion to the early students of Foster's work. Under the impression that they were counting only original works, they would include these titles in check lists of the composer's music. At one time, Foster Hall had credited Foster with over 300 original works. Gradually, through the discovery that this figure included "Derivata," the number was brought down to 201.
Foster Hall was a non-commercial institution. No charges of any kind were made for its services or its publications. Its founder did not seek self-advertisement. His only purpose was to revive interest in the music of Stephen Foster. All persons interested in Foster were cordially invited to visit Foster Hall or to correspond with Mr. Lilly. Writers and students seeking source material were especially welcome, and assistance was given to them in the preparation of article, book, or thesis. This liberal policy, for example, contributed to the production in 1934 of a long needed definitive biography of the composer, John Tasker Howard's Stephen Foster, America's Troubadour. This volume, the standard work on the subject, was not published by Mr. Lilly, but he had turned the facilities of his collections, both of materials and of newly-discovered facts of Foster's career, over to Mr. Howard, then already known as an able music historian through his reference book Our American Music. More than fifteen thousand visitors came to Foster Hall during its six years of existence in Indianapolis, not only from Indiana and the Middle West, but from other sections. At least once a week Foster programs were presented at the hall, consisting of a lecture on the composer, a display of the material in the collection, and Foster music by a quartet.
The publications of Foster Hall were prepared for many uses. The most important was entitled Foster Hall Reproductions of the Songs, Compositions and Arrangements by Stephen Collins Foster. This work is a set of facsimiles of the first (or earliest obtainable) editions of Foster's complete works. Since it serves as an accurate check list, it is a valuable aid to the collector who wishes to know the points determining the first edition of a Foster song. Because of the large number of Foster's works and of the necessity for accurate editing, the checking, engraving, and printing of the Reproductions was an undertaking of considerable magnitude, requiring a year and a half to complete. One thousand sets of the Reproductions were published and presented by Mr. Lilly to libraries throughout the United States and Great Britain. The fact that the Reproductions not only comprise Foster's complete works, but also are facsimiles of the original printings, makes them a unique publication.
Another widely distributed Foster Hall publication was a handsome reprint of the biographical section of Morrison Foster's work, under the title of My Brother Stephen. Other books and pamphlets, dealing with Foster's life, have been presented to collectors. Songs of Stephen Foster, edited by Will Earhart and Edward B. Birge, is intended primarily for use in schools. It is a collection of more than forty of Foster's best songs. This work has been widely distributed, and multiple editions were published by the University of Pittsburgh. Although prepared chiefly for use by children, adults found this work suitable for their own use. Mr. Lilly also published a number of arrangements of Foster's music. An excellent medley of Foster melodies for concert band was prepared by Luis Guzman, of the United States Marine Band. This work was presented to American high-school and college bands, and to bands throughout Latin America and Europe. The Foster Hall Recordings consisted of phonograph records of all Foster's original works. A few sets of these records have been prepared and presented to such institutions as the Library of Congress. Moreover, radio stations have been furnished phonographic recordings of Foster programs, and arrangements especially adapted for broadcasting purposes. In all his work, Mr. Lilly has attempted to do more than maintain a mere museum of Foster relics. He sought to keep alive the music of Stephen Foster. The Foster Hall publications not only helped to keep alive the best Foster melodies, they have helped to popularize songs of genuine merit, which were not so well known.
After he had founded his collection, Mr. Lilly seriously considered what should be done with it eventually. About that time, he heard of the Stephen Foster Memorial, planned by the Tuesday Musical Club and the University of Pittsburgh. There, it seemed to him, was the logical destination for his collection. His offer to present the collection to the Pittsburgh memorial was accepted, and in 1937 it was transferred in its entirety from Indianapolis to its new home. The work of Foster Hall, under the auspices of the University of Pittsburgh, was an uninterrupted continuation of its former activities in Indianapolis. Its facilities are available to student or writer, publications are sent out, schools and clubs are assisted in the preparation of Foster programs, the collection is exhibited to visitors, programs are held in the memorial.
Adapted from "A Pittsburgh Composer and His Memorial" by Fletcher Hodges, Jr. (Pittsburgh: The Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania, 1951)
Acquisition Information
Gift of Josiah Kirby Lilly in 1937.
Acquisition Information
The correspondence written prior to the 1937 transfer of the Foster Hall Collection was included as part of the gift to the University. The remaining correspondence was created/received at the University of Pittsburgh.
Popular music -- United States -- To 1901; Musicians -- United States; Music -- Manuscripts; Music -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864; Stephen Collins Foster Memorial (University of Pittsburgh); University of Pittsburgh. Foster Hall Collection
- A, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Contains correspondence from Aldine Book Co.; Alwes, Gladys; American Library Association; Antiquarian Magazine; Antiques; Appleton, D.; Mrs. A.F. Armstrong; Associated Music Publishers; Athens, PA Library; Mr. S.C. Atkinson; Mr. Axtell
- Aeolian Company, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Contains correspondence from the Aeolian Company in New York, NY, which produced three organ roles of Foster's music, not for sale or distribution, but for use at Foster Hall.
- B, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
- Bieber, Albert, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Correspondence from Albert Bieber, a Manasquan, NY, Antiquarian bookseller. Sold Lilly an entire set of Foster sheet music as well as songbooks with Foster interest.
- Boyd, Charles N., 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Correspondence from Charles Boyd, a Pittsburgh based Foster Fan. Boyd provided Lilly with many leads and contacts.
- Briggs, Morris H., 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Correspondence from Morris Briggs, a Chicago, IL, rare book dealer and one of Lilly's first contacts. Throughout the building of the collection he provided many interesting items, even though his prices were unreasonably high.
- C, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Contains correspondence from H. M. Caldwell Company; Calahan, Lorena; D.L. Chambers; Chappell Publishing Company, Ltd.; Cincinnati Enquirer; Cincinnati Music Hall; Circleville Public Library; Sherman Clay & Co.; Dr. J.B. Clayton; Mrs. J.L. Clough; Christopher Coleman; Madame Cooper; Charles Copeland; Sandro Corona; Monroe D. Crannell; Crooks; Frank Crumit
- Carnright, E.M., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Correspondence from E.M. Carnright, a New York, NY, dealer. All correspondence concerns the sale of sheet music.
- Certain, Mrs. Henry J., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Correspondence from Mrs. Henry J. Certain, from Huntsville, AL. From 1931 on Mrs. Certain was one of the main suppliers of sheet music to Foster Hall. Her prices were always reasonable, and her material in good condition. Lilly so respected her business-like attitude and high standards that she was one of his personal guests at the dedication ceremonies in Pittsburgh.
- Cravens, Miss Drusilla, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Correspondence from Miss Drusilla Cravens from Madison, IN. Although not a professional dealer, Miss Cravens unearthed many first and early editions of Foster's music. The Lilly Collection profited hugely as a result of her efforts. Strangely enough (or perhaps simply because she was not a professional) after this initial flurry of activity, Mrs. Craven did not continue to submit material to Foster Hall.
- Christopher, F., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Correspondence from F. Christopher, a South Orange, NJ, dealer, and one of the first and most consistent suppliers of sheet music.
- D, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Contains correspondence from L. Bryan Dabney; Dacs; Earl Daniels; Mrs. James W. Dansey; Herman Darewski Music Publishing Co.; Miss Ada Davis; William Dealtry; F.E. DeFrantz; Dellquest's Rare Book Shop; Mrs. James. D. Denegre; August De Prez; Diapason; Oliver Ditson Co.; F.L. Doherty; Dorrance & Co.; Alice Duck; Duttons Inc.
- Delano, Kirk, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Correspondence from Kirk Delano, from Canastota, NY. Not a professional dealer, Delano nonetheless supplied Lilly with a number of songbooks (mostly hymnals) containing Foster tunes.
- James F. Drake Inc. Rare Books and Autographs, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Correspondence from James F. Drake, Inc., of New York, NY. This dealer, in an attempt to secure material for Lilly, was the first to contact Evelyn Foster Morneweck in hope of purchasing music or Foster memorabilia. Mrs. Morneweck was unwilling to sell, so Drake put her in contact with Lilly. Although Drake did manage to secure some material for the Collection, he seems to have played a far more important role as a contact to other collectors. Drake also sold Lilly the slipcases for the books and other valuable materials in the collection.
- Driscoll, J. Francis, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Correspondence from J. Francis Driscoll from Brooklyn, MA. Both a dealer and an avid collection, Driscoll's large private collection formed the core of the Lilly collection. Although he kept in touch with the Hall over the years he had little to offer after the initial transaction.
- E, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Correspondence from R. Erdmans; Eaton Public Library; Emery Record Preserving Company; C.D. Eshan; Etude Music Magazine
- F, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Correspondence from the Filson Club; Carl Fischer Inc.; J. Fischer & Bro; Fitzgerald Publishing Co.; Forbes Library; B.S. Foster; Wm. B. Foster; Miss Electra L. Foster; Fowler; P. Ellwood Franklin; N.B. French; C.A. Fricke.
- G, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Correspondence from Lula Gans; Gatchill; Mrs. W.E. Gause; Colin Gilchrist; Eugene R. Gill; A.H. Godard; Graff Mr. E. Sloane; Mrs. Stewart A. Greene; K.S. Griswold; Frank C. Groover; Gerald D. Guise
- Goodspeed's Book Shop, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Correspondence from Goodspeed's Book Shop in Boston, MA. In 1930, this shop, acting as agent for J. Francis Driscoll, offered and sold to Lilly over 130 first editions of Foster songs. This was the first major purchase made by Lilly and became the core of the collection. Throughout the existence of Foster Hall, Goodspeed's continued to submit material.
- H, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Correspondence from Hall; Hall-McCreary; Harris; Heath; Heaps; Henkels; Heydenburk; Hildebrand; Hoban; Hobson; Hodges; Holcomb & Hoke Mfg. Co.; Hull; Hunleth Music Co.; Arthur Billings Hunt; Maude Hutchings
- Gordon, Hamilton A., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Correspondence from Hamilton A. Gordon Music Publishers in New York, NY. This company was the successor of the Horace Waters Co., publishers of some of Foster's original work. Gordon supplied Lilly with some "collateral Fosteriana" information on his publishers, etc.
- Goth, Marie, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Correspondence with Marie Goth of Nashville, TN. Lilly commissioned Miss Goth to paint a portrait of Foster, using the Riley portrait in Bardstown as a model. When completed, the painting hung in Foster Hall and Lilly had it photographed and mailed copies to many people on the Foster Hall mailing list.
- Grosvenor Library, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Correspondence with the Grosvenor Library in Buffalo, NY. Lilly exchanged first editions with this library, filling in gaps in each of the respective collections.
- Hollenbeck Press, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Correspondence with Hollenbeck Press in Indianapolis, IN. This company received a large amount of business from Foster Hall. They printed bulletins, stationary, and small chapbooks issued by Lilly. They did high-quality work and were on good terms with Lilly until right before the collection was transferred--at that time Mr. Krieg, the man with whom Lilly had all his dealings, retired and the new manager began raising prices causing Lilly to withdraw his business from the company.
- Hyne, C.W., 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Correspondence with C.W. Hyne in Utica, NY. Ms. Hyne was on the staff of the Utica Institute for the Training of Colored Men and Women and was the contact who introduced Mrs. Rose to Lilly. The Institute had a group called the Utica Jubilee Singers that performed many of Foster's tunes. Hyne broadcast Foster programs, including interviews with his descendants.
- I, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Correspondence with Indianapolis Athletic Club; Indianapolis Blue Print & Supply Co.; Indianapolis Electrotype Foundry; Indianapolis Engraving; Indianapolis Photo Co.; Elizabeth Ihr; Indianapolis Star
- Indiana State Library, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Correspondence with the Indiana State Library. Beginning in 1932 Lilly began to contribute unwanted sheet music from the Collection to the Library-- this material was generally not Foster related, but Americana. The library also received copies of the Foster Hall Bulletin and other Hall publications. In 1934 they were given a set of Foster Hall Reproductions. In 1935 the Indiana Library Association made Lilly an Honorary member.
- J, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Correspondence from Amos E. Jewett; W.R. Jillson; Merle Johnson; George Joplin
- K, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Correspondence from Eva Kaiser; Hope Kappes; George Kemp, Jr.; Kentucky State Library; Kentucky Playmakers; Kiger Burnett Company; Joseph Klem
- Kling, Mrs. Flora G., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Correspondence with Mrs. Flora G. Kling from Indianapolis, IN. It's unclear how she got in touch with Lilly. She was apparently elderly and handicapped and completely in love with Mr. Lilly even though they never met. She supplied a few items of interest to the collection.
- L, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Correspondence from Lamiza Lambert; Lester Levy; Liberty Engraving Company; Liebschutz Book Store; Eli Lilly & Co. Dr. John Uri Lloyd; Lorenz Publishing Co.; W.H. Lowdermilk & Co.; Lyon & Healy
- La Bree, Col. Benjamin, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Correspondence with Colonel Benjamin La Bree of Louisville, KY. La Bree was the curator of MOKH Commission when he first contacted Lilly in 1930. He had held the position for 9 years. Upon learning of Foster Hall he tried repeatedly--and unsuccessfully--to have Lilly hire him. In 1931 he was fired from MOKH. According to rumors, he took half of their belongings with him.
- Library of Congress, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Correspondence with the Library of Congress. Acknowledgements of materials Lilly donated.
- Lott, Mrs. Lorena Callahan, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 33)